guys let's find this limit it's the
limit as X approaches 0 of 1 minus the
square root of 1 minus X over X first
let's copy it down and let's try just
plugging in zero see what happens so in
the place of both these X's I just
plugged in zero well this minus zero
isn't doing anything and the square root
of one is just one and then one minus
one is zero by using direct substitution
we just got zero over zero which is an
indeterminate form this isn't giving us
any information given 0 over 0 the
answer could still be anything so we
have to find another way to solve this
looking at this I'm seeing a binomial
that includes a square root so usually
you're going to use the conjugate so in
this case 1 minus the square root the
conjugate would be one plus the square
root and then we're going to multiply
that to top and bottom so we're not
actually changing the value of the
rational expression so let's see what
happens when we use the conjugate on
bottom we're just going to leave it as x
times this we're not going to need to
distribute the X usually is the one that
isn't the conjugate you can just leave
it as the product of the two so now on
top let's multiply this stuff out so we
have 1 times 1 which will give us one
and we have one times the square root
which is the square root and then we
have the negative square root times 1
which is the negative square root and
then we have the negative square root
times the positive square root a
negative times a positive is going to be
negative and then the square root of 1
minus x times the square root of 1 minus
X when you multiply those the square
root goes away and we have 1 minus X so
before we simplify let's distribute this
negative to both of these terms so this
positive one will become a negative 1
and the negative X will become a
positive X so now we have the positive
of this square root and the negative of
this square root they're going to cancel
each other out and then we have positive
one and negative one those will also
cancel each other out and now let's
smoosh everything together and this X on
top and bottom will also cancel each
other out and now there's nothing on top
we should put the implied one now let's
do some direct substitution what happens
if we plug 0 into the X well the zero
isn't doing anything so this just
becomes one over one plus square root of
one and one plus square root one is one
plus one which is two and that is the
answer to our question let's put a box
around it so the limit as X approaches 0
of this is equal to one half and here it
is in Desmos and you can see that it
does approach one half from both
directions
if you guys want to try more of these
limit problems I have this page on
animat.com it's got a whole bunch of
problems with the answers the link is in
the description how exciting